<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dong Huynh - Research</title><link href="http://trungdong.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://trungdong.github.io/feeds/research.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://trungdong.github.io/</id><updated>2018-02-18T12:18:32+00:00</updated><entry><title>Provenance Network Analytics paper</title><link href="http://trungdong.github.io/provenance-network-analytics-paper.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-16T01:11:32+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T12:18:32+00:00</updated><author><name>Dong Huynh</name></author><id>tag:trungdong.github.io,2018-02-16:/provenance-network-analytics-paper.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10618-017-0549-3"&gt;&lt;img alt="Provenance Network Analytics paper - PDF version" src="http://trungdong.github.io/images/provenance-network-analytics-paper-title.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very pleased to announce that the above paper has been published in Springer's &lt;em&gt;Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery&lt;/em&gt; journal. It presents a novel approach to analysing provenance information, combining provenance network metrics and machine learning; the main aim currently is to label data from analysing their provenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10618-017-0549-3"&gt;&lt;img alt="Provenance Network Analytics paper - PDF version" src="http://trungdong.github.io/images/provenance-network-analytics-paper-title.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very pleased to announce that the above paper has been published in Springer's &lt;em&gt;Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery&lt;/em&gt; journal. It presents a novel approach to analysing provenance information, combining provenance network metrics and machine learning; the main aim currently is to label data from analysing their provenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10618-017-0549-3"&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt; and you can also get the PDF version directly at &lt;a href="http://rdcu.be/G3Nz"&gt;http://rdcu.be/G3Nz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the first time that I published all the data and code used to produce the paper's results online: &lt;a href="https://github.com/trungdong/datasets-provanalytics-dmkd"&gt;https://github.com/trungdong/datasets-provanalytics-dmkd&lt;/a&gt;
There, you can find notebooks describing the data preparation and the analyses shown in the paper along with some extra experiments that were not included due to space constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is it about?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, data analytics usually involves analysing the data themselves to discover patterns, outliers, and insights. In the paper above, we analyse instead the &lt;em&gt;provenance&lt;/em&gt; of the data, that is the historical record or the data describing its origins and what influenced its production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysing provenance records, however, is not straight-forward. Within the &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/"&gt;PROV data model&lt;/a&gt; that we use, there are three main provenance concepts: &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/#term-entity"&gt;Entity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/#term-Activity"&gt;Activity&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/prov-dm/#term-agent"&gt;Agent&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, there are 15+ possible provenance relations to link the three concepts, each of which has a specific meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we represent provenance information as a graph and analyse the topological characteristics of such a graph using network metrics, for example, measuring its size, diameter, or the distances between certain elements. By so doing, we can subsume provenance information into a set of numeric values reflecting the topology of its graph-based representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the numeric features from provenance information, we then apply off-the-shelf machine learning algorithms to build predictive models for properties of the data described in the provenance information. Using this approach, in three different applications, we could re-infer the owners of provenance documents, assess the quality of crowdsourced data from &lt;a href="https://collabmap.org/"&gt;CollabMap&lt;/a&gt;, and detect instructions from chat messages in an alternate-reality game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In brief, the approach aims to infer some properties of data from analysing the network features of the data's provenance information, hence the name &lt;strong&gt;Provenance Network Analytics&lt;/strong&gt;. One nice thing about this approach is that, apart from initial training examples, the predictive models can operate on provenance (represented using the PROV standards) without relying on domain-specific information. Therefore, it can serve as a generic data analytics tool in applications where provenance are captured or can be generated (from application logs, for example).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We describe the approach in detail in the paper. If you are interested to know more, go read the paper at &lt;a href="http://rdcu.be/G3Nz"&gt;http://rdcu.be/G3Nz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Analytics"></category><category term="Papers"></category><category term="Provenance"></category></entry></feed>